Actually,
其实一个人
no matter how much you earn,
你挣多少钱
or how high your position is,
当多大官
in the end, what matters most
到最后什么对你最重要
is your family.
家
Your mom and I
我跟你妈俩
are leading a life with
现在这日子过得就是
what people call the "Four Great Joys."
老百姓说的那四大香
Know what they are?
你知道吗
What are the "Four Great Joys," Dad?
什么是四大香啊 爸
Steamed buns, boiled chicken,
小笼包子 清炖鸡
morning nap, and old couples.
回笼觉 老夫妻
These are the "Four Great Joys" of people,
这是老百姓的四大香
you know?
你知道吗
The first three joys
前面这三大香
were given to us by you and Li Lin.
是你跟李临给我俩的
The last joy
后边这一香
was given to me by your mom.
是你妈妈给我的
No matter what,
不管怎么的
we are the whole family.
咱一家人在一起
When you get the chance in the future,
你将来有机会
you can start it all over again.
你再去干
I got your back.
我支持你
If not, remember
干不了了 你记着
that the light at home
家里那盏灯
will always be on for you.
永远为你亮着
Here.
给
What is it, Dad?
什么呀 爸
Take a look.
看看哪
Haowen, remember this:
浩文 你记着
no matter what happens,
不管到什么时候
we are always family.
咱们都是一家人
Diet control is very effective.
饮食控制 非常有效
Your blood pressure is basically normal.
血压已经基本正常了
However,
但是啊
you still need to
你要注意啊
exercise more,
还得多运动
at least ten thousand steps a day.
一天一万步
I know.
我知道
I've done this before.
又不是没生过
But it's different this time.
那可不一样
That was years ago.
那是多少年前的事了
Otherwise, it won't be easy.
不然 不好生
Okay.
好
You need to do some exercise.
多运动
I'll walk ten thousand steps every day.
我每天 一万步
Don't you need to work?
那你不工作了
Mom.
妈
Are you going for a walk?
你要出去散步吗
We can go together.
咱俩可以一起呀
Have you finished your homework?
你作业写完了
Yes, I have.
写完啦
Then, wait a moment.
写完了 你也等一会儿
We have something to discuss.
我有点事要说
Jing,
姐
you too, join us.
你 你也一起
Come here.
来
What's going on?
什么事啊
Are we having a family meeting?
开家庭会议吗
Alright.
好
I never know you have family meeting.
你们家爱开家庭会议呀
That's great.
真好 真好
Li Lin, come.
李临
We're having a family meeting.
快来 开家庭会议了
Coming.
来了
I'll take that.
来 给我
Well, you know,
是这样啊
I've
我呢
left my post.
离岗了
What does that mean?
离岗是什么意思呀
Does it mean you're unemployed?
失业的意思吗
It is leaving her post,
她这是叫离岗
not being unemployed.
不是失业
First of all,
一呢
it's because mom is pregnant.
是因为你妈妈怀孕了
Secondly, you're gonna have
二呢
the high school entrance exam.
中考嘛你
In this way she can accompany you.
可以陪着你啊
It's not like that.
不要乱说
It has nothing to do
跟 跟你一点关系
with you.
都没有
Don't feel burdened.
不要有心理负担
There was a problem at our company.
是我们公司出了点问题
It needs to be transferred.
要转让
So, the middle and senior management
然后我们这些中高层呢
like us will be in an awkward situation.
可能暂时不太好安排
Considering my current situation,
我一想我这个情况吧
I decided to take a long leave.
索性就休长假吧
It's called leaving the post,
说是离岗
which is almost like being unemployed.
可能跟失业也差不多了
I think it's good for you.
我觉得特别好
With your current situation,
你现在这个情况
nothing else is important.
其他的事情都不重要
You should stay healthy.
先把身体养好
You love working so much.
你这么爱工作
How could you be unemployed?
还能失业呀
No, it's temporary.
不 暂时的
Just temporary.
暂时的嘛
Not quite.
也不一定
It's true.
本来嘛
Well,
就
I haven't even given birth yet.
我这不是还没生呢吗
After giving birth, there's
生完了
still six months of maternity leave.
还有六个月的产假
We can't be sure what will happen
那到时候公司什么情况
in the company by then.
也不知道
Finding a new job
现在这新工作
is not easy these days.
又那么难找
So I thought
我就想着
I should explain the situation
把这个情况
clearly to all of you.
都跟你们说清楚
Mom,
妈
you love working so much.
你这么爱工作
But it comes to a sudden stop.
突然不工作了
Do you feel like a fish out of water?
是不是特别不适应啊
Do you see your mom as a workaholic?
在你眼里妈是个卷王吗
Not really.
那倒也不是
It's just that
就是
it'll be a tough time for your dad.
这段时间要辛苦你爸了
I'm fine, it's my duty.
我没问题 应该的
I'm fine, too.
我也没问题
Here's my promise.
我表个态啊
Mom, don't worry.
妈 你放心吧
I'll definitely work hard
我一定会
for the high school entrance exam.
好好准备中考的
I won't make you worry.
你 不让你操心
Here's mine too.
我也表个态
Taking care of you are the most
你现在是我们家
important thing in our family now.
最重要的事情
Don't worry.
你放心
I'll definitely
我一定会
do my best to take care of you.
尽全力把你照顾好
We will ensure the baby
咱们顺顺利利地
comes to the world safely.
把孩子生下来
This is the most important thing.
这个是最重要的
Nothing else matters.
其他都不重要
And I also want to
还有我想说的
tell you not to
就是经济上
worry about money.
你也别考虑
Look, we still have
你看咱们家
a clinic, don't we?
不还有一个诊所呢吗
Although it's currently
虽然现在是
managed by Mr. Ouyang,
老欧阳管着呢
but still,
但是
don't you worry about it.
你放心
You two have shares in it.
有你们俩的股份
Yeah...
不 姐
I'm not worried about the money.
经济问题我不担心
I have good news to tell.
我还有好事要宣布呢
Good news?
还有好事
Quick, tell us!
快说 快说
It's that
就是
Li Lin
李临
is going to work in Beijing!
要去北京工作啦
Great!
好耶
Does that mean I can
那我是不是
go sightseeing in Beijing?
可以去北京旅游了
How is that good news?
这是什么好事啊
Just sit down!
你 快快快 坐下
What kind of person are you?
你什么人哪
Your wife is about to give birth and
老婆现在马上就要生了
your daughter is about to take the exam.
女儿马上要中考
Are you working far away?
你还去外地
Do you have any sense?
你 懂不懂事啊
Jing...
姐
Jing, this is Li Lin's opportunity.
姐 这是李临的机会
He has to go.
他得去
Mom,
妈
if Dad goes to Beijing,
爸爸去工作
can he get a promotion?
是不是可以升职加薪呀
Even for a raise, he wouldn't go.
加薪咱也不去
Your mom's in a critical period right now.
你妈现在是非常时期
Do you understand?
你懂吗
Jing, don't get angry.
姐 你先别生气
I've thought about everything you said.
你说的这些我都想过了
But you've seen
但是这情况
the situation yourself.
你不是也看见了吗
I'm unemployed now,
我现在失业了
and we're having a second child.
然后还要生二胎
When the second child is born,
那二胎生出来
won't we need money to raise it?
不得花钱养啊
When Yunjie goes to high school,
云阶上高中
won't we have to pay tuition?
不得交学费啊
In this case,
这时候
someone in the family has to
家里得有一个人
work hard.
去拼一拼的
Besides,
再说了
even if he goes to Beijing,
就算他去北京了
at home,
家里头
you and Yunjie can take care of me.
有你跟云阶照顾我
What do I have to be afraid of?
我怕啥呀
Right?
是不是
Yes.
是
Don't worry, dad.
放心吧 爸
I'll take good care of Mom.
我会照顾好妈的
When you get to Beijing,
到时候到北京
remember to take me to eat roast duck.
记得带我去吃烤鸭
I mean
我想说
his current job
他现在这个工作
is okay, isn't it?
不是说还行吗
No, it's not.
不行
Beijing is better.
北京行
So he has to go.
所以他得去
I understand.
我明白了
Then it's
那就这么愉快地
a deal.
决定了
What's your deal?
定什么定啊
Did I say I'm going?
我说我要去了吗
How ridiculous.
莫名其妙
He...
他
He didn't say he was going, did he?
他没说要去啊
has to go.
得去啊
I...I'll go check on him.
我 我去看看他
You go check on him.
去看看 去看看
Come on, stop eavesdropping.
来 别听了 别听了
Why, auntie?
你干吗呀 大姑
Go back to your home.
回去 回去
Are you angry?
生气啦
Did Mei Yiduo go to you?
梅一朵去找你了
What did she say to you?
她跟你说什么了
She didn't say much.
也没说什么
Just...
就是
Why do you ask me out so urgently?
这么急约我出来
Is there something wrong
是李临那边
with Li Lin?
有什么问题吗
Nothing wrong with him.
没有问题
But Meng'an,
但是 梦安
I hope you can give Li Lin
我希望你能给李临师哥
a career opportunity.
一个事业上的机会
What opportunity?
什 什么机会啊
Didn't he tell you?
他没跟你说吗
Li Lin really is
我师哥果然是一个
a good man who puts family first.
顾家的好男人
What exactly is this opportunity?
到底是什么机会
Just tell me directly.
你直接跟我说吧
It's about working in Beijing.
是去北京工作的事
Actually, he already rejected me.
实际上他已经拒绝我了
But I don't want to give up.
但是我不想放弃
I still want to give it a shot.
我还是想再努力一下
Does he need to go to Beijing?
要去北京吗
I'm going back to set up a lab.
我要回国筹备实验室了
This is the plan I asked Li Lin
这个是我请师哥
to help me with.
帮我做的方案
He combined the domestic and international
他把国内外市场
markets and research needs
和科研需求
really well.
结合得特别好
This is something
这是我们所有人
none of us thought of.
都没有想到的
So I hope
所以我希望
you can persuade him to accept the offer.
你能说服他
After all, in the second half of life,
毕竟在人生的下半场
becoming the operations director
能成为顶尖实验室的
of a top laboratory
运营负责人
is an opportunity
这样的机会
that doesn't come often.
真的不多了
Are you mad at me?
真生气了
How can I not?
废话 我能不生气吗
Xu Meng'an,
许梦安
I'm over forty years old.
我四十多岁的人了
Don't I know
我该做什么
what I should do
我不该做什么
and what I shouldn't?
我心里不清楚吗
I don't need you to decide for me.
用不着你给我做主
In our family,
我们家里面
we always discuss everything
大大小小的事情
with each other,
我们彼此之间
no matter big or small.
都有商有量的
For such a big thing,
这么大的事情
you didn't talk with me.
你不跟我商量了
Where is the democracy?
民主在哪里啊
And what are those
平时说得天花乱坠的
sweet talks about?
那些事情呢
Do they count?
去哪里了
Have you ever respected me?
你有没有尊重过我
Great virtue promotes growth; knowledge and
厚德载物 知行合一
action are one. This is our school motto.
这是我们的校训
But it's not just a motto;
但它不仅仅是一句校训
it should be
它应该成为
a guiding light in our lives.
指引我们人生的
It's a beacon.
一盏明灯
Why do we study?
为什么要读书
It isn't just about learning knowledge.
读书不仅仅是学习知识
It's also about learning to respect others
更是要学会尊重别人
and our own dignity.
和自己的尊严
Where is my dignity?
我的尊严在哪里
You tell me.
我请问你
I didn't accept her offer.
我没答应她
Then what were you doing just now?
那你刚才在干什么
Talking nonsense
胡说八道的
about it's a deal.
定了 定了
What's the deal about?
定什么啊
I was just thinking
我这不是想着
about how I'll be out of work,
我工作没了吗
and we're expecting another baby.
然后又要生孩子
We'll be counting on you.
那家里就靠你一个人
Our living standards
生活水平
would just drop, wouldn't it?
不就掉下去了吗
Do you really care about that?
你在意这些吗
You don't need to act in front of me.
你不用跟我演了
You're talking nonsense again.
又在瞎说
I'm telling you,
我告诉你啊
I'm not going.
我不去
I have my own plans.
因为我有安排
I'm currently working for Director Ma
我现在在马所长那儿
and I've got a lab there.
有个实验室给我
And my income is good.
我收入也不错
If you think
如果你觉得
our living standards
我们的生活水平
could be improved a bit more,
可以再往上走一走
I can get another job.
我去打一份工可以啊
I haven't done it before.
我不是没打过
Is it necessary for you
你至于这样吗
to push me away like this?
一个劲把我往外撵
What do you mean?
什么意思
Who am I making space for?
我给谁腾地儿呢
I'm pregnant.
我怀孕了
You're pregnant now.
就是因为你怀孕了嘛
That's the very reason I can't leave.
那我更不能走了
I...
我 这
Isn't your sister here taking care of me?
这不是还有姐呢吗
What good is she?
她有什么用
Is she me?
她是我吗
Can she replace me?
她能替代我吗
Are you gonna spend your life with her?
你跟她过一辈子啊
No.
不
Then tell me
那你好好说
everything honestly.
你好好地跟我说
Tell me the truth.
说实话
If I could keep you by my side,
那要是能留你在身边
I wouldn't want you to go, either.
我也不想你走啊
Actually, I'm not forcing you
其实我也不是非逼着你
to Beijing to make money.
去北京挣那个钱
I just saw
我就是看见
that proposal
你给梅一朵
you wrote for Mei Yiduo.
做那个方案了
It was so thick.
这么厚
Looking at that proposal,
我看着那个方案
I thought
我就想
you must have a lot of ideas,
你肯定有特别多的想法
so you've written that much.
才写那么多的
If you can write that much,
那要是自己能写那么多
you must want to put it into practice.
肯定就会想去实践嘛
I think we're the same.
我觉得咱俩是一样的呀
Now you have a chance
你现在有一个机会
to become
能让你成为
the head of
顶尖生物实验室的
a top biology lab.
负责人
So...
那
Just go for it.
你就去呗
I know at your age,
我觉得你都这个岁数了
it's hard to have
再有这样的机会
a chance like this.
也很难了
Because of me and Yunjie,
你为我跟云阶
you've already missed it once.
已经错过过一次了
Although we're very happy,
虽然我们过得很幸福
but honey,
但是老公
I really regret it.
我真的后悔了呀
I regret bringing you back with me.
我后悔让你跟我回来了
I saw that thick proposal
我看着那么厚的方案
and realized
才知道
that all these years you never
你这么多年都没有
gave up on your dreams.
放弃过你的理想
I want you to give it a try.
我想让你去试试
Honey,
老公
please don't be angry.
你别生气了
Just go.
你去呗
I don't want you to regret it again.
我不想让你再后悔了
And don't make me regret it again.
你也别再让我后悔了
Will you?
行吗
Just do it for me.
你就当是为了我
Go and try it.
去试试呗
Why are you crying?
哭什么啊
You...Don't...
你 你别
Don't just stand there, come here.
别站着说话 来
I want a hug.
想抱抱
If you go,
你要是去了
remember to miss me.
你记得想我
My lovely wife,
老婆
you're really dramatic.
真的好能作啊
Adults are talking.
大人说话
Kids are not allowed to eavesdrop.
小孩不许偷听
Dad got mad.
我爸发火了
It's once in a blue moon.
千年难遇
I have to go and see it.
我得再去看看
Stop.
你停停停
Come back.
回来 回来
Why?
干吗呀
Go do your homework.
你写作业吧
I've finished it.
我写完了
Why don't you go find He Lu
要不你再找何璐
and hang out with her?
去玩玩
I'm not going.
我不去
I'm waiting for Dad
一会儿等我爸出来
to interview him.
我得好好采访采访他
Why doesn't he want to go to Beijing?
他为啥不想去北京呀
Stop adding to the chaos.
你就别跟着添乱了
Alright?
行不行
What's so good about going to Beijing?
去北京有什么好
Isn't our family good enough now?
咱家不好吗
But Mom wants him to go.
主要是我妈让他去
And he dares to resist.
他还敢反抗了
He even dares to lose his temper.
还敢炸毛
Dad is
我爸这是
about to rise up in the family.
要在家里翻身呀
Don't be stupid.
你说你这小孩
What are you thinking about
这脑子一天
in your mind?
都想些什么呀你
Anyway,
我不管
I vote yes.
反正我是支持
Dad should go to Beijing.
我爸去北京的
When he comes out,
等他出来
I'll have a good talk with him.
我就跟他好好谈谈
About what?
谈什么呀
Working in Beijing.
去北京呀
He could get a promotion.
还能升职加薪呢
What a thing to brag about.
这说出去多牛呀
He'd be a fool not to go.
不去是傻子
I think you're the fool.
我看你就是傻子
People say daughters
人家都说
are their mom's little comforters.
闺女是妈妈的小棉袄
Are you a qualified little comforter?
你这小棉袄怎么当的
Your mom is about to give birth.
你妈马上就要生孩子了
If your dad isn't here,
你爸不在
how can she feel at ease?
她心里能踏实吗
Aren't we both here for Mom?
这不有咱俩呢吗
And there are my grandpa and grandma
还有我外公和我外婆
and aunt Mengxin.
还有我小姨哪
There are so many people in the family.
咱家人也不少啦
But it's not the same.
这能一样吗
They're a couple.
人家是两口子
No one can replace your dad.
谁也代替不了你爸
Not even me.
我也不能
Why is it different?
怎么就不一样了呢
If it were me, I'd go to Beijing.
要我 我肯定就去北京
I really don't know what dad is thinking.
真不知道我爸怎么想的
He is just too dependent.
我爸就是太不独立了
If I were a senior, I'd definitely
我要是高三
study for a university in Beijing
我肯定就考到北京
to be a little further from my mom.
离我妈稍微远点
Didn't Cousin Hua
华华哥哥
go to Beijing for college?
不就考的北京吗
He must have thought the same as I do,
他肯定跟我想的一样
trying to be further from you, too.
也想离你远点
About the countdown to the exam,
这个中考倒计时
why didn't you write the time down?
你为什么不把时间写上
Why are you being so careless?
你为什么这么不用心哪
You don't seem urgent at all.
一点紧迫感都没有
How am I being careless?
我怎么不用心啦
I remember it in my head.
我都记心里啦
What's the use of just remembering?
记心里有什么用
I want to see your actions.
姑姑要看行动
Come on.
来吧
Auntie Jing will sit next to you
姑姑陪你
and help check your homework.
把作业再检查一遍
Come.
来
I'm here with you.
姑姑陪着你
Okay?
行了吧
Come, sit here.
来 坐这儿
I think it's better
我觉得
if my dad doesn't go to Beijing.
我爸还是不去北京好
Yeah.
对嘛
Exactly.
这就对了
It's better my dad takes care of me.
还是我爸管我好呀
Auntie Jing will help you
姑姑陪你
check your homework.
检查一下作业
Children's art class.
少儿美术班
Mind to take a look?
了解一下吧
No, thank you.
不用 不用
Children's art class. Come take a look.
少儿美术班 了解一下
Hello, little boy.
小朋友
Let me see.
我看看
Here you are.
你拿一个吧
No, thanks.
不要了
Children's art class. Come take a look.
少儿美术班 了解一下
Children's art class.
少儿美术班
Come take a look.
了解一下吧
No, I'm fine.
不用
Be careful.
慢点 慢点
Excuse me.
宝妈
Take a look at our children's art class.
少儿美术班 了解一下
Now,
我们现在
we'll give a small toy as a gift
登记试听课程
if you register for a trial class.
就可以送小玩具的
Would you like some small toys?
小朋友喜欢小玩具
We're gonna be late for class.
我们上课来不及了吧
Mom,
妈妈 妈妈
I want a little rabbit.
我想要只小兔子
We just need your contact information.
你 你留下联系方式
That's all.
就可以了
Maybe next time.
下次啊
Only your contact information.
记下联系方式就好了
Sorry about that.
不好意思啊
It's okay.
没事 没事
Do come and take a look at
了解一下
our training center later.
我们的培训机构
Come by when you have time.
有空来哈
Next time.
下次
You're so careless.
你怎么那么不小心啊
Look at what you've done.
你看给人家弄的
Be more careful next time.
下次小心一点啊
It was an accident.
我没看着
May I help you?
你好
Take a look at
了解一下
our art center.
我们艺术中心吧
Mr. Li.
李总
Stop calling me Mr. Li?
叫什么李总
Well,
那个
Monitor Li.
老班长
How are you doing here?
怎么样
Are you adjusting well
在我这店
in my studio here?
干得还适应吗
Yes, I'm doing well.
适应 适应
Thank you
谢谢你啊
for offering me this job.
给我这份工作
It's nothing.
这都不是事
No need to say that as we were classmates.
老同学不说这些
Come over for tea at my office.
去我那儿喝茶
Little Watermelon, Little Watermelon.
小西瓜 小西瓜
What do you see?
你看见啥了
What interesting things have you seen?
看见啥好东东了
What's over there?
那儿有啥呀
Tell them we don't smell.
你说我们 不是的
We're clean.
我们是 香香的
Isn't that right?
是不是啊
Let me see your hands.
我看 我看这手
It smells good.
香香的
We're in a great mood today.
我们今天心情可好了
Why are you so happy?
你怎么这么高兴啊
Dad,
爸
mom.
妈
I'm going .
我忙去了啊
Don't wait for me.
你们别等我了
Dad, I'm going.
爸 我忙去了
You're holding the bag upside down.
包拿反了
About face.
向后转
Forward
起步
march.
走啊
Goodbye.
再见
Bye, dad.
爸爸再见
I'm telling you,
我跟你说
this is our Haowen.
浩文就是浩文
As long as he gets out of this yard,
他只要出了这个院
there's hope for him.
那就充满希望
Indeed.
那是
Just look at who his father-in-law is.
你不看看那是谁的姑爷
Your dad is amazing.
爸爸太棒了
Look at your dad, fully revived.
你看你爸 满血复活
right?
是吧
Hello, mom.
喂 妈
Xin,
心心
I have good news.
告诉你个好消息
Haowen just went out.
浩文出去了
You mean Haowen went out?
你说浩文出去了
Where did he go?
他去哪儿了
I don't know.
不知道
He said
他说
he had something to do.
有事
He'll be back very late tonight.
晚上要很晚才回来
Alright, I got it.
行 我知道了
Don't worry about him.
你别管了
I'm so happy for him.
太好了
Let's go.
走
Where are we going?
干吗去啊
To the market.
菜市场
Well,
不是
hasn't Lanxiang already
兰香不是
bought a lot of groceries?
买了很多菜了吗
I want a salted fish to turn it over.
买条咸鱼
(To turn things around.)
翻个身
Xin.
心
Why are you here?
你怎么来了
I guessed you'd be here
我一猜你就在这儿
to hide from Mom and Dad.
躲爸妈呢吧
No,
没有
they've been nice to me.
他们对我挺好的
They've come to take care of
把照顾小西瓜的事
Little Watermelon from now on.
都揽过去了
I gave them a heads-up
我跟他们打预防针了
to leave you alone
让他们别管你
so you can be alone for a while.
让你自己待会儿
But they didn't listen.
说了也白说
They really are nice to me.
他们真的对我挺好的
Alright, I understand.
行了 我知道
With their
就他们那个
excessive enthusiasm,
过分热情的劲
even I want to come out
别说你了
and have some peace,
连我都想出来待会儿
not to mention you as a son-in-law.
自己清静清静
Is Xiongxiong out of school yet?
熊熊放学了
Yeah, he's been taken home.
早接回来啦
Don't worry.
你不用担心
Look, this is the good side
你看
about living with mom and dad.
跟爸妈住呢 就这点好
They can help us take care of the kids.
孩子都替我们照顾
We have nothing to worry about.
什么都不用操心
Right?
对吧
Yes, we've got
是 什么都不操心
nothing to worry about.
没有后顾之忧
But the nicer they are to me,
可是他们越这么对我
the more I feel
我心里越觉着
sorry for them.
对不起他们
Today, dad and I went to the riverbank
今儿爸把我叫到江边
and he talked to me a lot.
跟我说了好多
What did dad say to you?
爸跟你说什么啦
He told me not to give up.
爸跟我说也别放弃
He also said
还跟我说
that I should be
让我做一个
a responsible man.
有责任心的男人
It was so encouraging.
说得我热血沸腾的
But when I'm alone
但是我自己一个人
and calm down,
静下心的时候
I was wondering
我就在想
what else I could do
我还能干什么呀
and what our future would be.
未来是什么样
I really don't know what to do.
真的无所适从
In business,
做生意嘛
there are ups and downs.
它就是起起落落的
Isn't that normal?
这不是很正常吗
Now that
那 我们现在
we've returned to the starting point,
既然又回到起点了
let's pull ourselves together
那就收拾收拾
and start it over again.
整装再出发
Xin,
心啊
I've been thinking here all day.
我今天在这儿想了一天
What were you thinking about?
想什么呢
I was thinking
我在想
about how my business failed,
我生意怎么失败的
how I fell behind in the field,
怎么在商业上掉队的
how to catch up in the future,
我在想以后该怎么干
and what to do in the future.
该干什么
The more I think, the more I feel
越想我越觉着
confused.
挺迷茫的
You've only thought about it for one day.
你才想了一天
What can you figure out in one day?
你能想明白什么呀
Haowen,
浩文
you don't need to rush.
咱不着急
Let's take it slowly.
咱慢慢来
If you really feel that mom and dad's
你要实在觉得爸妈他们
excessive concern
他们太关心你了
would be a burden
对你是一种负担
or a distraction for you,
是一种干扰
I can
我可以在这儿
set up a table for you
就在这中间
right here.
在这儿支个桌子
Then you can come here to think.
你来这儿想
I believe
我相信啊
you'll figure it out.
你一定能想明白
Really?
真的吗
Of course.
当然了
After all, I'm here for you.
这不还有我呢吗
As long as we figure it out,
咱什么时候想明白了
we'll quickly put it into action,
咱就赶紧去做
just like we did ten years ago.
就跟十年前一样
We'll stand up
从哪儿跌倒的
from where we fell.
从哪儿爬起来
Can we still
咱俩还能
be like we were ten years ago?
像十年前一样吗
We definitely can.
一定可以啊
Guess what?
你知道吗
I called you today earlier
今天我给你打电话
but couldn't get through.
打不通
I guessed you must be here.
我一猜你就在这儿
Where is this place?
这儿是哪儿啊
This is where we started our career.
这儿是我们事业的起点
It's our lucky place.
是我们俩的福地
This lucky place
你能选这儿
will definitely help us make a comeback.
将来一定能东山再起
Alright,
行了
cheer up.
振作一点
What's the big deal?
有什么大不了的
We're already at rock bottom.
这都已经在谷底了
From now on, each way will be uphill.
今后怎么走都是上坡路
Hit me again.
再打一下吧
My hand is hurt.
打得我手都疼了
You do hit hard.
你可真舍得呀你
I'll go take the luggage downstairs.
那我先把行李拿下去啊
Alright.
好嘞
I'll have a few words for you.
我跟你们说几句
Have a seat.
坐
Here.
来
Our home
咱们家
is by the Fuchun River.
在富春江畔
Huang Gongwang's artwork
黄公望的富春山居图
Dwelling in the Fuchun Mountains depicts
画的就是
the very mountains and rivers here.
我们这里的青山秀水
There are lush forests and dense foliage,
林茂 丛密
surging river,
江水滔滔
fishermen casting their lines,
或渔人垂钓
and someone sitting alone in the picture.
或一人独坐
Yet between the strokes of the brush,
可是在笔墨之间
it's more about
更是透露着
reflections on life
一个不惑之年的游子
of a traveler in his middle age
对于生命的感悟
and the exploration of
以及家在哪里
the theme of where home is.
这个主题的探寻
Dear.
老公
I'm about to set off soon.
一会儿我就要出发了
I have a few words to say to you.
我有几句话想跟你们说
Yunjie,
云阶
time flies like
时光荏苒
a white horse passing through a gap.
如白马过隙
In a blink, you've grown up.
一转眼你这么大了
But you will always be
可是你永远是
daddy's beloved daughter.
爸爸的掌上明珠
Now, for you, Life is
人生对于你来说
just beginning.
刚刚开始
There's more
还有更多的精彩
brilliance ahead.
在等着你
Make sure to love yourself.
一定要爱惜自己啊
Dad has written a few words
爸爸写了几句话
and put the paper on your desk.
放在了你的桌面上
Do read them from time to time.
你要多看看
My dear wife,
老婆
you're expecting a child now.
你现在怀着孩子
In the days I'm away,
我不在的日子里
take good care of yourself
你要照顾好自己
and the baby.
照顾好孩子
Take some good rests.
多休息
Don't worry about me.
不用担心我
This will be
这一次
the longest we've been apart
将是你我认识之后
from each other since we met.
分开时间最长的日子
It's a test
对于我们两个来说
for both of us.
都是一次考验
After this farewell...
这一别
Dad,
爸
are you not gonna come back?
你是不打算回来了吗
Of course, I will.
我回来啊
Did I say I wouldn't come back?
我说我不回来了吗
Of course, I'll come back.
我当然要回来啊
This is my home.
这是我的家
Where else would I go?
我去哪儿啊
I'm telling you,
我跟你们说
I haven't left yet.
就是我现在还没有走
I feel like I shouldn't go.
我就觉得我不应该走
I don't want to leave.
我不想走了
It feels like I've already come back.
似乎我已经回来了
Hurry up,
快点吧
you're gonna be late.
时间都来不及了
Go quickly.
快走
I'm done talking.
我说完了
Do you have anything to say?
你们有什么要说的吗
Well,
那
then,
就
let's have a hug.
抱 抱抱呗
Let's have a hug.
抱抱
Yunjie,
云阶
let's go.
走了
Coming.
来了
Mom, I'm leaving for school.
妈 我走了
Okay.
好
Come here, give me a hug.
来 妈抱抱
Take some time to miss me.
要想我哦
Drive carefully.
开车慢点啊
Put the dishes there after finish eating.
那个 吃完了放那儿
I'll come back and do the dishes later.
一会儿我回来洗
Bye, Mom.
走啦 妈
Goodbye.
拜拜
Biparietal diameter is
双顶径
8.39 cm.
八点三九
Femur length is
股骨长
6.3 cm.
六点三
Head circumference is 29 cm.
头围 二十九
Abdominal circumference is 28.
腹围 二十八
Amniotic fluid
羊水嘛
is fine.
还可以
The fetus is perfectly fine.
胎儿发育正常
Please go to the
一会儿结束了
doctor's room after you've done here.
去诊室找主治医生吧
Okay.
好
Can you see if it's a boy or a girl?
你看这男孩女孩
It's not that clear.
这看不清啊
Did the ultrasound doctor tell you
超声检查大夫说了没
if it's a boy or a girl?
男孩女孩
We're not allowed to know it now.
人家现在不让说
Yes, right.
对对对
We are not allowed to be told.
不让说 不让说
We won't break the rules.
咱不违反规定啊
Sit here and wait for a while.
你坐这儿等会儿
I'll go buy you a bottle of water.
我去给你买瓶水
Alright.
好嘞
Sit here and take a good look,
你坐这儿再好好看看
and enjoy this moment.
高兴高兴
Here, be careful.
来 慢点
Honey,
老婆
how are you feeling?
感觉怎么样
I just had five tubes of blood drawn.
我刚都抽了五管血了
What do you think?
你说呢
Here,
来
have some chocolates
吃点巧克力
to recover yourself.
来补补血吧
I don't want it; it's too sweet.
不吃了 太腻了
Then have some fruit.
那吃水果吧
I also bought
我还买了
your favorite cherries.
你最爱吃的车厘子
Alright.
行
Look.
看
I've got you big cherries.
多大呀
Here.
来
You've suffered too much, honey.
辛苦了 老婆
Here, let me feed you.
来 我喂你
Here.
来
Here, I'll get you a tissue.
来 给你拿纸巾啊
Have another one.
再吃一颗
Where are shall we sit?
坐哪儿呢
Let's go there.
去那儿
Let me help you, honey.
老公喂
You must be tired, sit here.
累了吧 来
Okay.
行
You're all sweaty.
都流汗了
It's okay.
没事
Is it hot?
热不热
Let me wipe you off.
我给你擦擦
Don't be nervous.
不用太紧张啊
We must be careful.
可得小心啊
I bought some bread
这里还给你买了面包
and cookies for you.
还有饼干
Do you want more?
你还要吃吗
No, I'm good.
不吃了
Let's have some fruit.
我们吃点水果吧
Here, have another one.
来 再吃一颗
Hi, Ms. Wu.
吴老师
Xin, well done here.
心姐 你这做得不错呀
I still want to be a teacher.
我还是想转岗当教师
I used to study design.
我以前也是学设计的
Could you please help me with it?
你能不能带带我啊
Sure.
行
Then, please
那你
help me organize these students'
帮我把这些学生作业
assignments first,
先整理一下
then take photos
然后拍照
and send them to their parents.
发给他们的家长
Okay.
好的 好的 好的
No problem.
没问题
I'll start taking pictures right away.
我这就拍
Okay.
好
Thank you for that.
辛苦你啊
Not at all. My pleasure.
不辛苦 不辛苦
Sir, you can't sit here.
先生 这里不能坐
Mengxin, Mr. Li is looking for you.
梦心 李总找你
He wants you to go to his office.
让你去他办公室一趟
Got it.
我知道了
Why isn't she here yet?
咋还不来
Be patient! I just fetch someone for her.
急啥 她不叫去了吗
Xin, come here.
心心 来
Here.
来来来
Let me introduce someone to you.
我给你介绍个人
I know you want to be a teacher.
你不想搞教学吗
This is Secretary-General Chen
这位
from the association of art.
是协会的陈秘书长
In the world of art,
他在美术业界
he is highly influential.
那是一呼百应
Mr. Chen,
老陈
this is Xu Mengxin,
这是我跟你
one of my classmates
提起过的老同学
I mentioned before.
许梦心
So this is the campus belle
这就是你总说的
you've been talking about?
校花吧
I've heard a lot about you.
久仰大名
Nice to meet you.
你好 你好
You're indeed very beautiful.
果然很漂亮啊
No wonder you were campus belle.
不愧是校花
I'm too flattered.
李总抬举我了
I'm already
我都是
a mother of two kids now.
两个孩子的妈妈了
A mature woman
成熟的女人
would be more charming
才更有韵味
and more attractive,
更有味道
and know more about life.
更懂生活
Mr. Li,
李总
you have good taste.
有品位啊
I'll get some water for both of you.
我给二位倒点水吧
Black tea or green tea?
红茶 还是绿茶
Lemon tea.
柠檬茶
And you?
那您呢
The same.
跟他一样
Alright.
好好
Why too much touching?
咋还上手了呢
Isn't that part of social etiquette?
那不社交礼仪吗
You are nuts about her.
魂都飞了
Didn't you ask me
不是你让我
to evaluate her for you?
替你把关把关的吗
Did you just change
我说你最近这
your type lately?
口味变了啊
No wonder you
我说你咋
didn't bring young ladies
不带着年轻小姑娘
to our drinking parties anymore.
去咱那酒局了
Young ladies
年轻姑娘啊
are too shy.
太淡
Well, now you like
你现在这个品味啊
mature women.
成熟了
You've grown up,
长大了
starting to align with
你现在开始有点向我们
us artists.
艺术家靠拢了
How's going with that campus belle?
跟那校花 怎么样了
What do you mean?
什么怎么样了
She's just a classmate.
那是我同学
What classmate?
啥同学呀
Let me tell you.
我跟你说吧
Women like this have real charm.
这种女人 才有味道
She looks like
那一看就是那
a pampered rich wife.
养尊处优的阔太太
Interesting.
有点意思
What rich wife?
什么阔太太啊
She used to marry a rich man,
以前嫁了个有钱人
but her husband went bankrupt.
现在老公破产了
Beautiful as she was,
就她这条件
she looked down on everyone.
当年看得上谁啊
In her eyes,
我在人眼里
I was just a poor student.
那就是穷学生
Now,
现在
she's just begging
那不也一样
for a living at my studio here.
到我这儿 来讨口饭吃
You're such a coward.
你就是一   包
You've liked her for so many years.
你喜欢人家那么多年了
Why don't you
你还不赶快的
seize this opportunity?
趁热打铁 见缝插针
Are you waiting for the New Year?
你咋 你等着过年呢
Well, what opportunity?
不是 我插什么针啊
She's a mother of two kids.
那是俩孩子的妈
I'd be the one losing out.
吃亏的是我
You just...
你就
Mr. Li
李总
I...
我这
Here's yours.
你的茶
No, I'm fine.
不 不茶了 不茶了
Just put it down.
放下吧
Don't bother.
不茶了
You two beasts in human clothing.
衣冠禽兽
Mom, it's time
妈 到点了
to video chat with Dad.
该跟我爸视频啦
It's still a few minutes away.
还有几分钟呢
Why are you so strict about a video call?
视个频这么严谨干吗呀
Meng'an.
梦安
Are you
你这是
still at work?
还没下班呢
I'm working overtime today.
今天加班呢
Everyone is here.
都在这儿
Time you to show us something.
到你展示的时间了
Let's see
让我们看看
what you're doing now.
你在干什么呀
Wanna see my workplace?
想看看我的环境啊
Look.
你看
This is my office.
这是我办公室
Over here,
这边
my colleagues are all here.
大哥哥大姐姐们都在呢
This is my daughter.
我女儿
Hi.
你好 你好
Everyone's greeting.
都打招呼了
Hello.
你好
Mom, look.
快看啊
No, I'm not.
我不看
You talk to your dad.
你跟你爸说吧
Where is the beautiful lady?
那个漂亮阿姨呢
You mean Miss Mei?
你说梅阿姨啊
She was here a moment ago.
刚才那会儿还在呢
I don't know where she is now.
这会儿不知道去哪儿了
Well done, Mr. Li.
表现不错 老李
Again, here are the
我再跟你说一遍
key points for you:
知识点啊
video chat with my mom
每天晚上七点
every evening at seven;
和我妈视频
attach locations to your WeChat Moments,
发朋友圈要记得带定位
so we will know
让我们时刻知道
your whereabouts.
你的行踪
These are all key points, okay?
这都是考点 好吗
Okay.
好的 好的
Don't just give me key points.
你别光给我划考点
Have you mastered the key points
你这中考的考点
for the high school entrance exam?
你都掌握了吗
Don't worry.
你放心吧
My mom and my aunt
现在有我妈和我大姑
are taking care of my studies.
四只眼睛盯着我学习呢
I'm almost driven crazy by them.
我都快被她们烦死了
Dad,
爸
I really miss you now.
我现在可想你了
I miss you too, Yunjie.
我也想你 云阶
Exam preparation is truly important,
这 备考归备考
but you also need to rest.
劳逸结合
Eat something good and sleep well.
该吃吃 该睡睡觉
Okay, got it.
好的 好的
I'll give you and mom five minutes
给你和我妈五分钟时间
to talk privately.
让你俩单独聊
Here.
给
Well, close the door.
那个 把门关上
Hello.
喂
I'll go outside and talk to you.
我出去跟你说啊
We're eating meals here,
咱们哪 吃的是盒饭
while Director Li is showing us romance.
李主任那撒的是狗粮
Director Li
李主任啊 每次吃饭
will report his schedule to his wife
都要准时准点地
every day at dinner.
给太太报备行程
It's their family rule.
人家啊 那是家规
What kind of family rule?
那什么家规啊
Isn't that just being henpecked?
那不就是妻管严吗
That's loyalty.
人家那叫规矩
Do you understand?
你懂不懂
What kind of loyalty?
什么规矩啊
It's the restraint of love.
爱的约束呗
No wonder you've been single these years.
活该你一辈子单身狗
Is it close to the due date?
快到预产期了吧
Not yet, there's still a month.
早呢 还有一个月呢
Still a month?
还有一个月呢
Didn't the doctor say
大夫说
that Little Grape's
这个
had adequate months?
小葡萄不是足月了吗
Doesn't that mean
是不就意味着
you could give birth any time?
随时都可能生产啊
It's okay.
还好吧
I've taken time off.
我请了假了
I'll be back this weekend
周末我就能回来
and the week after next week.
下下周呢 我也能回来
Is that okay to take so much time off?
你请这么多假 好吗
Why don't you
要不你还是
wait until the due date
等着预产期的时候
and come back then?
一块儿吧
I've already requested time off.
我都请完假了
Mei Yiduo also agreed.
梅一朵也同意了
Anyway,
反正
I still have maternity leave.
我这不是还有产假吗
But don't take too much
那 那你产假也别休
maternity leave.
太长时间了
Don't be like Haowen who
你别跟浩文学
took two months of maternity leave
休两个月产假
and left the company bankrupt.
把公司都休黄了
Now the whole family depends on you.
现在咱家可全靠你了
I'm not trying to pressure you.
我可不是给你压力啊
I know what I'm doing.
我自己有把握
Honey.
老公
Babe.
老婆
I miss you.
我想你了
I miss you, too.
我也想你了
Take care of yourself
你一个人在那边
since you're all alone there.
好好的
I'm doing good.
我都挺好的
No need to worry about me.
你也不用担心
Okay?
好不